Jan Wojcik papers 1945-1996 CPAA 05-14
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University, New Britain
Jan Wojcik papers
1945-1996
Wojcik, Jan
CPAA 05-14
1 box (1 linear ft.)
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University
Jan Wojcik was a prolific writer and essayist, and also dedicated community activist and a patriot. Wojcik was born in Russia in 1913, but after the Bolshevik war he returned to Poland in 1921. He lived and was educated in Poland. In 1939 he served on the front as an artillery officer. He was captured by the Germans and spent the rest of the war in a POW camp. After the war ended he immigrated to Brazil in 1949 and later to the US in 1961. He lived in New Britain and worked in manufacturing and tersely for the Polish cause. He wrote to several Polish and Polish American periodicals and participated in activities of many Polonia organizations. His collection consists of his writings, articles and books.
Historical/Biographical Note
Jan Wojcik was born in Rostov, Russia in 1913, where his father attended the university and worked after graduation. He returned to Poland with his parents in 1921 after the Bolshevik war. Mr. Wojcik was educated in Poland and graduated from the Reserve Artillery Officers Academy.
During World War II he served as an artillery officer and was captured by the Germans after capitulation of Warsaw in 1939. He spent the rest of the war in a German prison camp. After the war ended Poland was under Russian occupation and forced him into exile. For the first four years after the war he worked in a Relief Society for Poles in British occupied Germany. He immigrated to Porto Allegre in Brazil in 1949, where he was very active in Polish émigré community. Mr. Wojcik wrote extensively to local press and to Kultura, a political and literaly emigre magazine published in Paris, France, and also produced a weekly Polish radio program. Mr. Wojcik immigrated with his family to the United States in 1961 and settled in New Britain. He worked in the manufacturing business and continued his involvement in Polish causes. He was actively involved in activities of numerous Polonia organizations such as, Haller Post Polish Army Veterans, Choir Polonia Paderewski, Solidarity International, Radio "Solidarnosc", and Polish American Congress. Jan Wojcik continued to write countless articles on political issue and about history and culture of Poland and published in Kultura, Listy do Polakow and Gwiazda Polarna. Wojcik's radio commentaries were published by the Polish Studies program at Central Connecticut State University in 1993, entitled "Drodzy sluchacze" (Dear Listeners) a compendium of 430 commentaries and essays. In 1995 Jan Wojcik was decorated with Cavalier Cross of the Order of Merit of the Republic of Poland. In 1996 Polish American Congress of Connecticut choose Mr. Jan Wojcik for the Man of the Year award.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The collection consists of Mr. Wojcik writings and published books, articles and essays and limited correspondence.
The collection is open for research.
Material in the collection was donated by Mr. Wojcik in 2005.
Search Terms
Jan Wojcik; Danuta Wojcik; Stowarzyszenie Weteranów Armii Polskiej w Ameryce.; Placówka 111 im. Gen. Hallera (New Britain, Conn.).; Holy Cross Church (New Britain, Conn.).; Polish Americans -- Connecticut.; Radio broadcasting, Polish -- Connecticut.; Immigrants -- Connecticut.; Polish people -- Brazil -- Biography.; Polish Americans -- Connecticut -- Societies, etc.; Polish Americans -- Connecticut -- New Britain.; Correspondence.; Scrapbooks.; Photographs.; Clippings.
Related Material
For related material see the following collections:
Mieczyslaw Kierklo papers CPAA 87-47
Czeslaw Gieniewski papers CPAA 08-09
Arrangement
Material in the collection is arranged by date.
Container List
[The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.]
- Jan Wojcik - obituary., 2009 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Jan Wojcik - Man of the Year Award - Polish American Congress, district of Connecticut., 1996 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Jan Wojcik - letters, postcards., 1976, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Scrapbook: pictures, clippings, postcards from various Polish cities, with special wooden cover engraved with Polish flag and white crowned eagle, on the back engraving: Relief Society for Poles in Germany., between 1945-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "Weselisko" a play by Danuta Wojcik, Porto Alegre., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Articles and essays written by Jan Wojcik and published in periodical Skarb Rodzinny., 1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Piecdziesiata rocznica "Cudu nad Wisla", essay by Jan Wojcik., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- O Sowietach, Azji i Bliskim Wschodzie, series of articles written Wlodzimierz Baczkowski, published by Kultura. Bound in red, black and grey leather, gilded inscriptions, color handmade frontispiece. Bound by A. Dziwura, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Józef Pilsudski w relacjach i ocenach,zebral i zestawil Józef Weisbach, 329 leaves, printed in Chicago., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Echa z Polski, scrapbook by Jan Wojcik, includes postcards, photographs, clippings about Polish politicians (Pilsudski), towns and national shrines., undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Books by Jan Wojcik available at the Central Connecticut State University Library: Drodzy sluchacze: 430 pogadanek w "Glosie Solidarnosci", New Britain, Connecticut 1983-1992; Balcerowi nastepcy, 1975; Polonia w/in Connecticut, 1966; Z dziejow zolnierza-emigranta: historia "Haller Post" w New Britain, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 11)